<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bitscrafter – Products</title>
    <link>https://bitscrafter.com/products/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Products on Bitscrafter</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    
	  <atom:link href="https://bitscrafter.com/products/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      
        
      
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Overview - Web of Trust</title>
      <link>https://bitscrafter.com/products/overview_web_of_trust/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bitscrafter.com/products/overview_web_of_trust/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://bitscrafter.com/images/logo.png&#34; alt=&#34;logo&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://bitscrafter.com/images/products/wot/banner.png&#34; alt=&#34;Banner&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://bitscrafter.com/images/products/wot/patent-certificate_48x48.svg&#34; title=&#34;Patent Pending&#34; alt=&#34;Patent Pending&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Patent Pending&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Problem Statement&lt;span class=&#34;hx-absolute -hx-mt-20&#34; id=&#34;problem-statement&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#problem-statement&#34; class=&#34;subheading-anchor&#34; aria-label=&#34;Permalink for this section&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Contextual data to deliver personalized experiences constitutes an essential need of modern digital ecosystems that
increasingly rely on autonomous software entities—including AI agents, applications, and services. This data is often
sensitive and belongs to specific entities (persons, organizations). However, enabling these autonomous entities to
access such data at scale, in a secure manner and while preserving privacy, presents fundamental challenges that
existing industry standards fail to adequately address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AI Agent View&lt;/strong&gt;
Autonomous entities face a critical operational constraint: they must access sensitive data from numerous providers to
function effectively, yet each provider requires confidence in the entity&amp;rsquo;s trustworthiness. Traditional approaches
require manual registration with each data provider—establishing credentials, undergoing verification, and negotiating
access terms. This model fails at scale: an agent serving millions of users cannot feasibly pre-register with every
potential data source, especially when processing requirements emerge dynamically during operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User View&lt;/strong&gt;
Users face a trust evaluation challenge before engaging any autonomous entity: they must assess whether a previously
unknown agent is legitimate, identify its controlling organization, understand its security practices, and determine if
it merits access to sensitive data. Current approaches lack mechanisms for presenting verifiable evidence of an agent&amp;rsquo;s
trustworthiness and organizational backing. Without this foundational trust assessment, users cannot make informed
decisions about establishing relationships, yet subsequent data sharing consent decisions depend entirely on this
initial determination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Provider View&lt;/strong&gt;
Data providers face a real-time verification challenge: they must dynamically evaluate an entity&amp;rsquo;s trustworthiness at
the moment of first data access request, often without prior relationship or interaction history. Current approaches
lack common industry-adopted, programmatic mechanisms to verify an unknown entity&amp;rsquo;s legitimacy, organizational backing,
and user authorization in real-time. This forces data providers to choose between denying access (blocking legitimate
use cases) or implementing manual registration processes that cannot scale for autonomous operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These challenges become acute in autonomous operations where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Discovery: Agents dynamically encounter new data sources during operation based on evolving processing needs,
making the scaling of pre-established relationships increasingly impractical when serving millions of users across
potentially hundreds or thousands of data providers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Entity Trustworthiness: Without pre-established trust credentials, each data provider must independently verify an
autonomous entity&amp;rsquo;s legitimacy and trustworthiness on-the-fly prior to authorizing data access, thus creating
redundant verification overhead across data providers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-Entity Collaboration: Autonomous operations typically involve multiple entities working together—agents
coordinating with third-party services, LLMs, and data processors—yet users lack visibility into this collaboration
chain, cannot grant granular permissions to each participant, or maintain accountability for operations across the
ecosystem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solving these challenges requires a comprehensive framework that enables dynamic trust establishment, real-time
verification, and transparent multi-entity coordination while maintaining user control and cryptographic accountability
throughout the data lifecycle&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;System Overview&lt;span class=&#34;hx-absolute -hx-mt-20&#34; id=&#34;system-overview&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#system-overview&#34; class=&#34;subheading-anchor&#34; aria-label=&#34;Permalink for this section&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Web of Trust (WoT) system addresses the challenges outlined in the problem statement by creating a comprehensive
framework for managing trust, relationships, consent, and data access across organizations, users, autonomous entities,
traditional applications, and services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WoT operates as a trusted intermediary that integrates existing trust establishment mechanisms (e.g., X.509 Certificate
Chains, OpenID Federation) with OAuth2/OIDC protocols while extending them to support dynamic autonomous entity
operations, explicit multi-party relationships, granular consent management, and cryptographically accountable data
access throughout the entire lifecycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://bitscrafter.com/images/products/wot/wot_system_overview_black-white-gray.png&#34; title=&#34;System Overview&#34; alt=&#34;System Overview&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;System Overview&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Details&lt;span class=&#34;hx-absolute -hx-mt-20&#34; id=&#34;details&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#details&#34; class=&#34;subheading-anchor&#34; aria-label=&#34;Permalink for this section&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The diagram illustrates WoT&amp;rsquo;s end-to-end operation through four interconnected phases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.a. Organizational Trust Establishment:&lt;/strong&gt; Organizations undergo identity verification through external trust anchors
(X.509, OpenID Federation) or WoT-orchestrated processes, resulting in verified WoT registration with cryptographic
credentials. Once registered, organizations can create delegated entities (agents, applications, services) that inherit
trust from the parent organization while maintaining their own authentication credentials and operational independence.
Each organizational entity generates cryptographic key pairs and registers their public keys with WoT, with a strong
recommendation for their private keys to be managed through secure crypto modules (e.g., HSM, TPM, Keychain) for
subsequent authentication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.b. User Trust Establishment:&lt;/strong&gt; Users establish their identity through FIDO2/WebAuthn authentication, with optional
identity verification for enhanced trust relationships. Users can register with or without verified identity, though
verification enables access to more trust-sensitive interactions. Even without formal identity verification, the FIDO2
authenticator provides cryptographic proof that the current user is the same person who registered the account and
possesses the registered device, establishing the foundation for subsequent consent and authorization decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Trustworthy Relationship Formation:&lt;/strong&gt; Organizations and users, having already established their trust credentials
independently, can now form explicit relationships within WoT. Prior to approving any relationship, WoT verifies the
requested relationship parameters against the parties&amp;rsquo; pre-existing trust establishment proofs and credentials. WoT
registers approved relationships with defined scopes, constraints, and cryptographic accountability, enabling subsequent
mediation of consent and data access requests based on these pre-established trust relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3a. WoT Consent Formulation:&lt;/strong&gt; When an organizational entity requests access to user data, WoT implements a two-layer
consent architecture. In the WoT layer, WoT presents a granular consent request providing detailed information about
which specific organizational entities (not just the parent organization) will access data, what specific data types
each entity requires, conditions and constraints on data usage, evidence of why these entities are trustworthy based on
their verified credentials and relationship parameters, and the purpose and duration of data access. Users can grant,
deny, or conditionally approve consent with fine-grained control over data sharing across multiple entities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3b. IdP Consent Formulation:&lt;/strong&gt; In the IdP layer, users interact with the Identity Provider&amp;rsquo;s standard OAuth2 consent
interface, which serves as the actual authorization mechanism for data access. WoT&amp;rsquo;s consent layer acts as an
enhancement wrapper around this traditional OAuth2 consent, providing multi-entity visibility and trustworthiness
assessment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Data Access Authorization:&lt;/strong&gt; After user consent is obtained, WoT authorizes organizational entities to access the
specified user data. WoT retrieves data from user-authorized sources, validates that the requesting entity&amp;rsquo;s credentials
and session are current and valid, verifies the access complies with consent parameters and relationship constraints,
and securely delivers the data through end-to-end encrypted channels. Every data access operation is cryptographically
logged for auditability, enabling users to review which entities accessed what data types and when, with the ability to
revoke access or modify consent at any time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This integrated approach ensures that trust flows seamlessly from external verification through relationship formation,
consent management, and data access, enabling secure autonomous operations while maintaining cryptographic
accountability and user sovereignty over their data and digital relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Participating Entities&lt;span class=&#34;hx-absolute -hx-mt-20&#34; id=&#34;participating-entities&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#participating-entities&#34; class=&#34;subheading-anchor&#34; aria-label=&#34;Permalink for this section&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Web of Trust ecosystem comprises multiple entity types organized in three concentric layers: External (where
third-party entities provide trust services), Identity &amp;amp; Relationships (where organizations and users establish verified
identities and relationships), and Web of Trust (where WoT mediates relationships, consent, and data access).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://bitscrafter.com/images/products/wot/wot_participating_entities_black-white-gray.png&#34; title=&#34;Entities&#34; alt=&#34;Entities&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Entities&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Entity Categories&lt;span class=&#34;hx-absolute -hx-mt-20&#34; id=&#34;entity-categories&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#entity-categories&#34; class=&#34;subheading-anchor&#34; aria-label=&#34;Permalink for this section&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The participating entities are organized into two primary categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Registered Entities&lt;/strong&gt;: Digital identities established and managed by WoT, including organizations, users, and their
delegated entities (agents, applications, services, devices). These entities can form relationships, grant consent, and
access or provide data within the trusted ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supporting Entities&lt;/strong&gt;: External entities that provide trust establishment, consent management, and data access
services. These entities operate independently of WoT but integrate with the system to enable its comprehensive trust
framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Registered Entities&lt;span class=&#34;hx-absolute -hx-mt-20&#34; id=&#34;registered-entities&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#registered-entities&#34; class=&#34;subheading-anchor&#34; aria-label=&#34;Permalink for this section&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User Entities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User:&lt;/strong&gt;
Individual entity that owns personal data and establishes relationships with organizational entities requiring data
access. Users have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Personal preferences and privacy requirements that inform consent decisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Legal rights under privacy regulations (GDPR, CCPA, HIPAA) that the system must respect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiple concurrent relationships with different organizations and their entities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Authentication capabilities through FIDO2/WebAuthn credentials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Users authenticate using FIDO2 authenticators that provide:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cryptographic proof of user verification (biometric or PIN confirmation)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Device possession verification (authenticator security)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explicit consent binding (user presence confirmation)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Users may undergo optional identity verification through external providers, with verification status affecting which
relationship types they can establish. Even without formal verification, FIDO2 authentication establishes cryptographic
proof that the current user is the same person who registered the account and possesses the registered device, providing
the foundation for consent and authorization decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User Device:&lt;/strong&gt;
Physical or virtual device entity owned by an individual (smartphone, tablet, laptop). User devices:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Establish and maintain secure execution environment based on device authentication credentials stored in consumer
crypto modules (FIDO2 authenticators, Keychain, Keystore, platform security modules)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host user applications and store user credentials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintain security boundaries between applications to protect credential isolation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optional registration with WoT enables enhanced security posture through device-level authentication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organization Entities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All organizational entities authenticate using asymmetric cryptography, providing cryptographic proof of entity identity
and private key possession. Private keys must be stored and managed through secure crypto modules (HSM, TPM, Keychain)
to prevent unauthorized access and enable non-repudiation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organization:&lt;/strong&gt;
Business entity that offers software entities (agents, applications, services) to perform tasks for users.
Organizations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Undergo mandatory identity verification through external trust anchors to establish WoT registration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Establish cryptographic credentials verified through trust chains from Certificate Authorities, OpenID Federation, or
KYB providers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create and own delegated entities that inherit organizational trust while maintaining independent authentication
credentials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assume legal liability for actions of their delegated entities through cryptographic attestation of ownership&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintain organizational policies governing entity behavior, data handling, and relationship management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agent:&lt;/strong&gt;
Software entity that operates with varying degrees of independence on behalf of an organization to provide services to
users. Agents can make context-driven decisions and take actions within well-defined parameters, making them
particularly suitable for AI-powered services that require adaptive behavior. Agents:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make decisions and take actions within parameters established by relationship constraints and organizational policies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Operate across multiple platforms and interact with other agents, applications, or services with varying degrees of
independence, from fully independent to human-supervised operation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May require dynamic access to contextual data from multiple sources to support decision-making and adaptive behavior&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Must obtain explicit user authorization to access data according to their operational requirements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cryptographically sign all data access requests with credentials derived from organizational trust&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agents represent the primary use case driving WoT&amp;rsquo;s design, as AI agents particularly benefit from dynamic data access
capabilities, cross-organizational operation support, and verifiable accountability mechanisms that enable independent
operation while maintaining user control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Application (App):&lt;/strong&gt;
Software entity with specific functionality that operates on behalf of an organization to provide services to users.
Applications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Typically have defined user interfaces and operate within single platforms or environments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Execute predetermined functions with well-defined behavior patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Require explicit authorization to access user data based on functional requirements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Authenticate using organizational crypto module credentials inherited from parent organization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Service (Svc):&lt;/strong&gt;
Backend software entity that provides specific functionality without direct user interaction. Services:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Operate continuously or on-demand to process data, perform computations, or integrate systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May be invoked by applications, agents, or other services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Require explicit authorization when processing user data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cryptographically authenticate using credentials establishing organizational ownership&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organization Device:&lt;/strong&gt;
Physical or virtual device entity representing server infrastructure or enterprise hardware owned by an organization.
Organizational devices:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Establish and maintain secure execution environment based on authentication credentials stored in enterprise crypto
modules (HSM, TPM, secure enclaves)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host multiple agents, applications, or services with isolated execution environments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintain security boundaries between organizational entities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Authenticate using crypto module credentials proving device identity and authorization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Supporting Entities&lt;span class=&#34;hx-absolute -hx-mt-20&#34; id=&#34;supporting-entities&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#supporting-entities&#34; class=&#34;subheading-anchor&#34; aria-label=&#34;Permalink for this section&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supporting entities operate in external layers and provide essential services that WoT integrates into its trust
framework. These entities are grouped by the lifecycle phases where they participate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust Establishment Phase&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust Anchor (TA):&lt;/strong&gt;
Root authority in a trust hierarchy that establishes foundational trust. Trust Anchors include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Certificate Authorities (CA) in X.509 PKI ecosystems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trust anchors in OpenID Federation hierarchies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other recognized sources of cryptographic identity verification&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trust Anchors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide cryptographic validation of identity claims and credentials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Issue signed attestations (certificates, entity statements) binding identities to public keys&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Operate independently of WoT as external sources of trust&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enable verification without requiring online connectivity to the anchor (through signature validation)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identity Verification Provider (IVP):&lt;/strong&gt;
External service that verifies the legal or real-world identity of users or organizations. IVPs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perform identity proofing through document verification, biometric checks, or authoritative database queries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Execute Know Your Customer (KYC) verification for individuals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Execute Know Your Business (KYB) verification for organizations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Issue verification attestations that WoT uses to establish verified identity status&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide evidence documentation supporting verification decisions (identity documents, verification methods, assurance
levels)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verifiable Credential Issuer (VCI):&lt;/strong&gt;
Entity that issues cryptographically signed credentials attesting to specific claims. VCIs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Issue credentials conforming to W3C Verifiable Credentials Data Model or related standards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sign credentials with issuer&amp;rsquo;s private key enabling independent verification&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include identity attributes, organizational affiliations, certifications, or permissions in credentials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enable credential holders to present claims to relying parties without contacting issuer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support decentralized identity verification models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consent Formulation Phase&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identity Provider (IdP):&lt;/strong&gt;
External service that manages user authentication and authorization for data access. IdPs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement OAuth 2.0 and OpenID Connect protocols&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Authenticate users to verify data ownership before authorizing access&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Present standard OAuth 2.0 consent interfaces for authorization decisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Issue access tokens to authorized clients (WoT in this system) for subsequent data retrieval&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manage token lifecycle (issuance, renewal, revocation) according to OAuth 2.0 specifications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work with Data Providers to enforce access control decisions based on user consent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of IdPs include Google Identity Services, Microsoft Entra ID, Apple Authentication Services, and other major
identity providers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Access Authorization Phase&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Provider (DP):&lt;/strong&gt;
External entity that hosts or controls user data that organizational entities wish to access. Data Providers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement access control mechanisms validating authorization tokens before releasing data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accept OAuth 2.0 access tokens issued by IdPs as proof of authorization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Respond to authorized data requests based on token scope and user consent parameters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May be operated by the same organization as the IdP or be separate entities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintain their own security policies and access controls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Log data access for their own audit and compliance purposes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data Providers trust IdP-issued tokens rather than establishing direct trust relationships with every potential client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Entity Relationships&lt;span class=&#34;hx-absolute -hx-mt-20&#34; id=&#34;entity-relationships&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#entity-relationships&#34; class=&#34;subheading-anchor&#34; aria-label=&#34;Permalink for this section&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;These entities interact across the three trust layers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;External Trusted Root, Consent &amp;amp; Data Access:&lt;/strong&gt; Trust Anchors, Identity Verification Providers, and Verifiable
Credential Issuers establish foundational trust for initial registration. Identity Providers manage OAuth2
authorization, while Data Providers host user data and enforce access control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trusted Identity &amp;amp; Relationship:&lt;/strong&gt; Organizations and Users register with WoT using credentials verified by the
External Trusted Root, then form explicit relationships defining scopes, constraints, and permissions for data access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trusted Web:&lt;/strong&gt; This layer brings everything together—Organizations&amp;rsquo; delegated entities (Agents, Applications,
Services, Devices) use established relationships to request data access, navigate WoT&amp;rsquo;s consent framework, obtain IdP
authorization, and retrieve data from Data Providers, all mediated by WoT&amp;rsquo;s orchestration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WoT orchestrates interactions between these entities, ensuring that trust established in external systems flows through
relationship formation and granular consent to secure data access decisions within the trusted web.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
